Brockton, Mass. South Congregational Church records, 1835-1979.
Congregational Library Archives
Brockton, Mass. South Congregational Church records, 1835-1979.
RG5394
Congregational Library Archives
1.79 Cubic Feet
(3 boxes)
In 1836 a significant portion of the members of the First Parish Congregational Church withdrew their membership to form the South Congregational Church in Plain Village, now Campello, Brockton. The first meeting house was constructed in 1836 and The South Congregational Church of North Bridgewater was formally gathered on January 3, 1837 with Rev. John Dwight as the first minister. On May 23, 1853, the first meeting house was destroyed by fire; the second meeting house was constructed a year later. The South Congregational Church in Brockton merged with the First Parish Congregational Church, Porter Congregational Church, and Waldo Congregational Church to form the Christ Congregational Church in 1980. This collection contains the records of the South Congregational Church in Brockton and includes the surviving administrative, fiscal, legal, and vital membership records of the church.
Hope Chapel (Brockton, Mass.)
South Congregational Church (Campello, Brockton, Mass.)
Restrictions on Access
Access to this collection is unrestricted and open to the public.
Acquisition Information
Materials were donated to the Congregational Library & Archives by the South Congregational Church in 1980. Materials were sepparated out of RG0037 in March, 2019; Accession 2019-03.
Historical Note
In the early 1830s the area of North Bridgewater, now Brockton, called Plain Village, now Campello, was growing rapidly. The inhabitants of Plain Village had to travel about a mile and a half to attend service at the First Parish Congregational Church. In response to this long travel distance, it was decided that Plain Village should support a new church. In 1836 a significant portion of the members of the First Parish Congregational Church withdrew their membership to form the South Congregational Church. Construction on the first meeting house was begun on July 4, 1836 and the building was dedicated on December 29, 1836. The South Congregational Church of North Bridgewater was formally gathered on January 3, 1837. The Rev. John Dwight became the first minister of the church in 1837.
On May 23, 1853, the first meeting house was destroyed in a major fire which consumed a total of 11 buildings. A new building was erected the following year and the dedication of the second meeting house took place on September 21, 1854. The spire, which originally stood at 185 feet, was blown over in a wind storm in 1857. The spire was replaced and reduced so that it only stood at 135 feet. In 1892 the Hope Chapel was constructed and dedicated about a mile from South Church. The chapel remained active until 1906 and was then sold. In 1896 Memorial Hall was constructed and attached to the church; the Sunday school and many of the church groups met regularly in the hall. Memorial Hall was refurbished and rededicated in 1936 as part of the centennial celebrations of the church. The church was incorporated under Massachusetts law in 1901.
The South Congregational Church in Brockton served the Campello community until 1980 when it merged with the First Parish Congregational Church, Porter Congregational Church, and Waldo Congregational Church to form the Christ Congregational Church. The second meeting, which stood at the corner of Main and South Street, no longer stands.
Scope and Contents
This collection contains the records of the South Congregational Church in Brockton. The collection contains the administrative, fiscal, and legal records of the church. Included within the collection are the records of the church and parish, vital membership records, financial records, building and pew records, and various legal documents.
Arrangement
Materials have been arranged into the two series listed below. Within each series, materials have been arranged in chronological order, by start date, primarily, and by topic secondarily.
Series 1: Church and Parish records, 1836-1979
Series 2: Financial and legal records, 1835-1941
Related Materials
In 1980, the First Parish Congregational, South Congregational, Porter Congregational, and Waldo Congregational Churchs merged into a single entity, the Christ Congregational Church. The records of all four churches are held at the Congregational Library & Archives:
Brockton, Mass. First Parish Congregational Church records, 1738-1980.
Brockton, Mass. Porter Congregational Church, 1800-1979.
Brockton, Mass. Waldo Congregational Church, 1896-1980.
Bibliography
100th Anniversary of the Building of the Present Edifice. Brockton: South Congregational Church, 1954. 17.11.1 B78.33 ChrCC
Baptismal records.; Church bells.; Church finance.; Church membership.; Church records and registers.; Marriage records.; Pews and pew rights.; Brockton (Mass.) -- Church history.; Campello (Brockton, Mass.) -- Church history.; Hope Chapel (Brockton, Mass.); North Bridgewater (Mass.) -- Church history.; Plain Village (Mass.) -- Church history.; South Congregational Church (Campello, Brockton, Mass.)
- Church and parish records, 1836 1979; 1836-1979; 20 Files; (10 volumes, 10 folders)
  Scope and Contents
  This series contains records related to the administration of the church and parish society, as well as the vital records of church members and church services of order. Also included in this series are the records of the Hope Chapel, a short lived outreach church.
  - Parish records, 1836 1906; 1836-1906 (Box 1, Volume 1)
  - Parish records, 1906 1917; 1906-1917 (Box 1, Volume 2)
  - Church communications, 1836 1838; 1836-1838 (Box 1, Folder 1)
  - Clippings, 1836 1914; 1836-1914 (Box 1, Folder 2)
  - Dedications and anniversary programs, 1836 1954; 1836-1954 (Box 2, Folder 1)
  - Church records, 1837 1889; 1837-1889 (Box 1, Volume 3)
  - Church records, 1837 1918; 1837-1918 (Box 1, Volume 4)
  - Church records, 1890 1901; 1890-1901 (Box 1, Volume 5)
  - Church records, 1914 1937; 1914-1937 (Box 1, Volume 6)
  - Catalogue of members, 1837 1897; 1837-1897 (Box 2, Volume 1)
  - Catalogue of members, 1837 1897; 1837-1897 (Box 2, Volume 2)
  - Membership list, 1842 1917; 1842-1917 (Box 2, Volume 3)
  - Membership lists, 1866 1906; 1866-1906 (Box 2, Folder 2)
  - Miscelaneous events and church memorabilia, 1887 1894; 1887-1894, undated (Box 2, Folder 3)
  - Hope Chapel records, 1902 1904; 1902-1904 (Box 1, Volume 7)
  - Annual reports, 1907 1965; 1907, 1962-1965 (Box 2, Folder 4)
  - Historical sketches and research, 1936 1941; circa 1936-1941 (Box 3, Folder 3)
  - Annual reports, 1966 1971; 1966-1971 (Box 2, Folder 5)
  - Annual reports, 1972 1979; 1972-1979 (Box 2, Folder 6)
  - Self-study report, 1971 (Box 2, Folder 7)
- Financial and legal records, 1835 1941; 1835-1941; 13 Files; (7 volumes, 6 folders)
  This series contains records relating to the fiscal and legal operation of the South Congregational Church. This series contains treasurer's reports, pew deeds and subscriptions, insurance policies, and building related purchases.
  - Pew subscriptions and account book, 1835 1869; 1835-1869 (Box 3, Volume 1)
  - Deeds, 1836 1918; 1836, 1874-1918 (Box 1, Folder 3)
  - Treasurer's book, 1837 1904; 1837-1904 (Box 3, Volume 2)
  - Treasurer's book, 1905 1915; 1905-1915 (Box 3, Volume 3)
  - Treasurer's reports, 1910 1917; 1910-1917 (Box 1, Volume 8)
  - Purchase of bell, 1853 (Box 3, Folder 1)
  - Insurance policies, 1853 1854; 1853-1854 (Box 1, Folder 4)
  - Pew subscriptions, 1854 1867; 1854-1867 (Box 3, Volume 4)
  - Parish collections, 1877 1878; 1877-1878 (Box 3, Volume 5)
  - Certificates of incorporation, 1901 1918; 1901-1918 (Box 3, Folder 2)
  - Organ fund, undated (Box 3, Volume 6)
  - List of treasures, undated (Box 3, Folder 4)
  - Pew payments, undated (Box 3, Folder 5)